California Governor Gavin Newsom is expected to sign a law that would ban the sale of
new gas powered cars in that state by the year 2035.
It would not outlaw however those cars owned at the time.
This comes on the heels of major federal legislation aimed at boosting the electric vehicle market
and Illinois legislation attempting to do some of the same.
But are consumers ready to make the switch?
Joining us are Dave Sloan, President of the Chicago Automobile Trade Association and
Jen Walling, Executive Director for the Illinois Environmental Council.
We welcome both of you to Chicago tonight.
So Jen, we've got the Inflation Reduction Act.
We have recently passed Illinois legislation that had tax credits for electric vehicles.
Just remind us of all the potential tax incentives here for those who want to purchase an electrical
vehicle or a charging station.
Absolutely.
So the Climate and Agricultural Jobs Act that was passed last year has a $4,000 rebate for
each vehicle that hasn't gotten a rebate before.
Those are underway right now as of July 1st.
There also is an up to 80% rebate for the installation of electric vehicle infrastructure
in our homes.
Those are easily Googleable.
You can find them on Google, find the information out there, get it through the dealer.
The Inflation Reduction Act added to that with an additional tax credit, $7,500 for
a new vehicle and $4,000 for a used vehicle, as well as copious money for charging infrastructure
throughout the country.
And Illinois also passed tax credits for electric vehicle manufacturing to be located
here in the state.
So a number of incentives that can stack on top of each other.
A lot of potential incentives, although Dave Sloan, let's take a look at the average price
for an electric vehicle right now.
I believe it's around $65,000, just over $65,000.
And there's some worries that EV manufacturers might boost the price to offset this new federal
tax credit.
Do you think all these incentives will bring those prices down for consumers and make them
more affordable?
Well, one problem with these recent incentives is they're very restrictive as to where the
batteries are, the materials for the batteries are extracted and also where the vehicles
are made and then what's the income of the consumer.
So we're hoping that over time those will become less restrictive and more available
to more consumers.
But I don't think you'll see the manufacturers raising the price to offset the incentive,
but obviously they have been raising prices because of the cost of the materials.
Right.
A big issue with inflation and supply chain issues right now.
So Jennifer, to that California law that is expected to be signed by the governor, 2035
banning the sale of new gas-powered cars, how big of an impact could that have?
I think California passing that is huge.
California was first with the clean car standards that have been really important to encourage
EV manufacturing in the state.
I think that impact can't be underestimated.
And I know Illinois is going to be far behind.
We haven't even enacted the clean car standards yet or some of the heavy-duty truck standards.
So I think we have a lot of work that we need to do in the state, but it is really promising
and it'll increase the electric vehicle market here in Illinois.
Dave Sloan, could an action like that in California move the market in a big way to EVs?
Well, the point, what's more important is the auto manufacturers are all in on EVs.
I mean, they are spending tens of billions of dollars investing in the EV technology,
new EV vehicles, and they're coming fast here over the next few years.
So I think, and we've seen, we produced the Chicago Auto Show, we've seen more and more
people interested in EVs taking test drives and so on and indicating their interest.
So I think the demand is going to be there.
We'd always rather see consumer demand move the market rather than government mandate
because EVs might not be good for everyone.
You know, you can see someone in rural areas who have to tow things.
EVs just might not be the right answer, but certainly for suburban and city applications,
they would work much better.
So it's hard in a state like California or even one like Illinois to have a blanket mandate,
much rather see consumer demand.
And it certainly seems like we're going that way.
Jen Walling, I want to pick up on that point.
I have a friend that just moved from LA to Chicago and he had to ship his electric vehicle
here because he found there was no way to drive across the country.
So far behind are we as a nation and Illinois as a state in setting up the infrastructure
to be able to drive EVs wherever you want.
Looking at the infrastructure in Illinois, there is infrastructure that accommodates
most mileage.
Some of it you are going to have to stop at a fast charging station for 20 minutes.
You may have to stop for longer at some of the slower charging stations, but there's
infrastructure that exists.
We do need to bulk it up.
We need to have more fast charging stations.
We need to provide more routes and more information for people.
I think that some of those consolidated maps are yet to be fully complete.
And there's so much more charging that's coming.
Some of the groups that are coming in that might be companies are not as transparent
or open about where they're going to put their charging stations.
And we wish we could see a little more of that so that we can plan as a state for when
and where electric vehicles are going to go and where the infrastructure routes will
go.
But our state is making a lot of progress and people can confidently make a road trip with
most vehicles in Illinois.
Dave Sloan, what about that?
How far away is the U.S. from being able to have an EV driver go from Yuma, Arizona to
Laramie and not have to worry about finding a charging station?
Well, you know, certainly more needs to be done.
The cars are smart, too.
There's so much intelligence in the vehicles.
They'll be able to tell you how much charge you have left and where you need to go to
get your car fast charged.
We'll start seeing things like that.
So lots to be done, though, in terms of infrastructure.
If you're a condo owner and is your condo association going to let you put a level two
charger in your garage, those kinds of things need to happen for more people to get into
the EV market.
How easy is it for apartment dwellers?
There's a company called Escalant that does a lot of research in the EV category.
And they say that most new car buyers are homeowners.
So that will, you know, so you're assuming they have garage to charge their vehicles.
I've been driving an electric vehicle since 2013 and I charge my vehicle at my garage.
I charge it at work and it works out well for me.
Jen, while you mentioned that Illinois is behind the curve on just enacting mileage
tangent, things like that, are groups like yours going to lobby the General Assembly
for a law like the one being considered in California banning the sale of new gas powered
cars down the road?
The dominant will be lobbying on transportation issues.
But we are far behind California, as I mentioned.
I have to do my due diligence is starting.
We need to make active transit and bike safety and public transit better first.
Those need to be priorities, but electrification is vital to the transportation sector.
We're going to need it.
And there's so much in terms of the car standards, the alternative clean truck
standards for one of several states.
There's a bipartisan group of governors that signed on to a heavy duty MOU for semi trucks
and light trucks.
That's really important for environmental justice communities, particularly in Chicago.
So those are all things that we're going to need to do within our state.
The governor Pritzker and his team have really led on new policies like manufacturing.
But there are a number of other policies that we need to put into place before we're heading
in that direction.
So I'm hoping we see the General Assembly and the IEPA take action on those.
All right.
Very interesting discussion.
We're going to have to leave it there.
Dave Sloan and Jen Walling, we appreciate it.